Burling, Temple Papers /4153
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Temple Burling Papers
1949-1974
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Burling, Temple
/4153
5 cubic feet
5 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
8016933
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, December 17, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 03, 2016
Biographical / Historical
Temple Burling (1896-1975)
Temple Burling was a member of the faculty of the School of Industrial and Labor Relations from 1948 until his retirement in 1964. During the first two years he served half-time in the mental health program of Gannett Clinic, later continuing to practice psychotherapy there for one afternoon a week. Dr. Burling was a pioneer in the field of industrial psychiatry. With R. H. Macy and Company (1937-40), he was the first psychiatrist to serve full time on the staff of a business or industrial firm. During this same period he was publishing the first articles outlining how the psychiatrist could ease the emotional tensions people encounter in work situations. At Cornell he succeeded Alexander H. Leighton as the director of the ILR Industrial Psychiatry Program. This program provided young psychiatrists with internships in industry, under the guidance of the director and in consultation with other faculty members.
Dr. Burling is survived by his wife, Mrs. Katherine Burling of Trumansburg; a daughter, Helen Ottaway of Johnson City; two sons, Robbins Burling of Ann Arbor, Michigan, and James Burling of Oswego; seven grandchildren; a sister, Helen Kronwall of Tucson, Arizona; and a cousin, Edward Burling of Washington, D.C., Douglas Darling, Alpheus W. Smith, William F. Whyte, Cornell University.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4153 AV: Temple Burling Audio-Visual Materials 5730: John H. Cornehlsen Papers
Burling, Temple.
8016933
- Material from Turkish sabbatical; Misc. Files; Corresp. From 30s and 40s (Box 1)
  - Curiculum Vitae, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Misc. Correspondence, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Medical Licenses, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters Misc. 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1954, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence 1951, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence 1949-56, 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters Misc. 1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters Misc. 1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters Misc. 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Group Therapy Association-1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters 1938, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Finnestead Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mrs. Shelberg, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dr. Burling Personal-1942, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sex Book and Talks, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Scope and Contents
    Dr. Burling
  - Miss Ann Kenerson, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    The AID Memoire U.S.A.I.D. Turkey
  - Lease, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    From Miss Ann Kenerson To: Dr. Temple Burling
  - Orta Dogu Teknik Universitesi, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes on Winnetka students Faculty, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Papers etc. Reading notes etc., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - A.I.D., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Whitehead, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Reseancle, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Albany, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Percoptron Notes (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Treatment of Group O, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Chapter 21. Interdepartmental Relations (Folder 1 of 2), 1961-1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Chapter 21. Interdepartmental Relations (Folder 2 of 2), 1961-1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Turkey M.E.T.U, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Maruyama, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - M.E.T.U., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - M.E.T.U. Impressions, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Autobiographical Sretches Janet Sperber, Peter Atteslander etial, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence 1974 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - European Addresses, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - European Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - European Reprints, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Drug Inventory, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Branetti, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Lawton, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Harry Stack Sullivan Bibliography, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Wilson Bob, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Turkey, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Turkish Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Stamps Foreign, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Misc. Files; Materials from 2nd sabbatical in Turkey (Box 2)
  - "Farewell Book" to Dr. Temple Burling, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Farewell Letters, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Psychiatrists, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Misc., 1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    One photograph of Helen Letitia Thompson April 16, 1939
  - ORTHO- Function and Training, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Med. School (Folder of 1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    The Plaqysma, Neurology Note-book.
  - Med. School (Folder of 1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Physiology 12 Laboratory Notes
  - Rehab Leaflets, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pre-Industrial Human Relations, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The University of Western Ontario School of Business Administration Letters and Misc. Docs. (Folder 1 of 2), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Misc. Documents- Temple Burling, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - GAP, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - William Hone George Crukshank (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Original Research in Medicine and Chemistry since 1896
  - Johann Weyer (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Original Research in Medicine and Chemistry Since 1896
  - George III 1738-1820 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Assorted Pamphlets (Folder 1 of 2), 1939-1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Examples: Journal of Social Casework, Therapeutic Investigations in Schizophrenia Rodent Damage to some booklets
  - Assorted Pamphlets (Folder 2 of 2), 1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Rodent Damage on some booklets
  - Human Relations, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Benjamin Rush (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Elmira Research Meeting and Misc. Docs., 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sigmund Freud (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Self Conscious Society, Roundtable A + Misc. Docs., 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lake Logan Conference, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Misc. pamphlets + Some Effects of the Changing Work Environment in the Office, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Himler, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - A Psychiatric Contribution to the Development of Executives + Other Documents, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Industrial Psychiatry, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Today's Industrial Psychiatry + Bibliography for Industrial Psychiatry and Neurology (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Himler, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Mainly sabbatical - 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Powell Case, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notes on First Sabbatical Trip, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Addresses European, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rochester Child Study Dr. Aldrich, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 160 E 21, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 160 E 20, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Proceedings of the Conference on Medical and Health Problems in Areas of AJDC Activity- partially in French
  - Thompsems County Med Faculty, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Some booklets in German and French
  - Silvius, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Most documents in French
  - T. Burling MILR Written, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Dr. Temple Burling 208 Hobel Caltan Helmiah (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - From Sabbatical 1956-57, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters Answered US, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Checks, Check book, Pocket book Receipts, USA, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    These seem to be from Sabbatical in 1956-57
  - US Addresses, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sterling Project, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Curriculum Vitae Meun, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Brunetti, 1949-1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Cryptograms (Folder 1 of 3), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Cryptograms, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Cryptograms (Folder 3 of 3), 1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Employment Information for different people (Folder 1 of 5), 1954 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Employment Information for Diff. People (Folder 2 of 5), 1949 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Employment Information for Diff. People (Folder 3 of 5), 1955 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Employment Information for Diff. People (Folder 4 of 5), 1958 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Employment Information for Diff. People (Folder 5 of 5), 1955 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Articles, reprints (Box 4)
  - American Orthospychiatric Association, Inc. Meetings 15-17 and Administrative Science Quarterly, 1938-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - New Approaches in Management Organization and Job Design- II + Misc. Documents, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlets by Temple Burling, 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    You can't hire a hand, Essays on Human Aspects of Administration, Psychiatry in Industry etc.
  - New Approaches in Management Organization and Job Design- II and other articles by Temple Burling, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Articles by Temple Burling (Folder 1 of 2), 1959 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Articles by Temple Burling (Folder 2 of 2), 1947-1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Brief Communications, Life Experiences as Therapeutic and other articles by Dr. Burling, 1934-1952 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Articles by Temple Burling (Folder 1 of 6), 1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Articles by Temple Burling Teaching at ILR (Folder 2 of 6), 1940 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Articles by Temple Burling (Folder 3 of 6), 1939-1949 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Articles by Temple Burling (Folder 4 of 6), 1938 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Articles by Temple Burling (Folder 5 of 6), 1954 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Articles by Temple Burling (Folder 6 of 6), 1932-1936 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Articles by Temple Burling, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Mss. For book; Material Burling wrote while at Macy's [?] ('37-'40) (Box 5)
  - Movies, Bib, Misc. etc. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - A Management Coaching Program for Union Bag & Paper Company- Temple Burling, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - GAP, 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Proposed Dept. 41 Procedures, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Pamphlets, 1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Essays on Human Aspects of Administration. International Psychiatry Clinics, You can't hire a hand, Day In, Day Out
  - Diary and Other Papers by Temple Burling, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    This Seems to come from T. Burlings Time at R.H. Macy's 1937-1940
  - Chapter I to XI (Folder 1 of 6) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Chapter IX (Folder 2 of 6) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Chapter I to XI (Folder 3 of 6) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Chapter I to IX (Folder 4 of 6) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Chapter I to XI (Folder 5 of 6) (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Missing Chapter 9
  - Assorted Chapters and Writings (Folder 6 of 6) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Robs Notes (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Critique: Dr. Burling's Book (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - A Manuscript Criticism ILR 624 Dr. Burling, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Some Comments by the Reader over my Shoulder, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    L.D. Fernald, JR. ILR 624
  - Reports/ Critiques of Dr. Burling's book, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Clinical Treatment of Group Problems ILR 624 James A Pierson (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Some Questions on the Forthcoming Book of Dr. Temple Burling (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - "The Group Is the Patient" Temple Burling (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Chapter I To XI (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Extra Copy of Chapter 10
  - Stenated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - 2nd Draft Complete (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Bibliographies I.L.R. 624, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - References, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Paper for ILR 624 Criticism of Book Richard Warnecke, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Occupational Stress, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Bibliographies and Memorandum, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Occupational Medicine, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Licenses, 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Odd ments, 1948-1964 (Box 5, Folder 31)